Thomas Gray Manuscripts:
Thomas Gray Archive
- Poems, [ca. 1725]-1771; mss.poems
  - Elegy Written in a Country Churchyard, The curfew tolls the knell of parting day; 1751; poems.elcc
    - Stanza written in a Country Church-Yard, [1750?]; mss.0040; poems.elcc; 4 transcript in an unidentified hand; HARV
      Houghton MS Eng 116.1-8 contain Gray autographs and copies of manuscripts written by or concerning Thomas Gray. Houghton b MS Eng 116.6 (Papers on Thomas Gray) contains photostatic copies of commonplace books, journals, notes, travel notebooks, poems, and other materials chiefly from Pembroke College (Cambridge) and the Pierpont Morgan Library.
    - Stanzas Written in a Country Church Yard, [not later than 1794]; mss.0041; poems.elcc; 5 transcript in an unidentified hand 315 mm x 196 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 04/11/2006.
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=138995>
      Transcript in an unidentified hand, entitled Stanzas Written in a Country Church Yard, in a volume entitled Hardwicke Papers, vol. DCCCCXXII.
    - [untitled], [1753?]; mss.0042; poems.elcc; 1 transcript, partial [4 lines]
      Catalogue of a Sotheby's sale (10 December 1913), lot 67, facsimile in catalogue
      An unlocated transcript of the "Redbreast stanza" in a copy of Designs ( 1753 ) was sold as autograph, Sotheby's ( 10 December 1913 ), lot 67 (with a facsimile), it was sought by J. Hayward in The Book Collector 5 (1956), 384-385.
    - [untitled], [after 1775]; mss.0212; poems.elcc; 2 transcript in an unidentified hand, partial [8 lines]; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Transcript in an unidentified hand of 8 lines (one stanza after l. 100 and the "Redbreast stanza" after l. 116) with the former only in the Eton MS, with notes, in a copy of the Elegy, 8th edition (London, 1753), 10-11, bound in a volume entitled Poetical Tracts.
      MS 0212 apparently transcribed from MS 0043.
    - Elegy written in a Country Church-Yard, 1780[?]; mss.0230; poems.elcc; 11 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/03/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled Elegy written in a Country Church-Yard (p. 117) (Elegy. [p. 119]). The poem, which in this version has four unique readings ("winds" for "wheels" [l. 7], ", the" for "and" [l. 32], "to" for "on" [l. 68], and "sage" for "swain" [l. 97]), is part of a section called Poems, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 129), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
    - [untitled], [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0210; poems.elcc; 2 transcript of variant lines in the hand of John Mitford, partial 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Transcript of variants of several lines, headed "Various Readings in his Poems, from MSS.", in the hand of John Mitford, in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", ff. 180r, 181r.
      MS 0210 apparently transcribed from MS 0043.
    - The Elegy, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0211; poems.elcc; 2 transcript of variant lines in the hand of John Mitford, partial and crossed out 180 mm x 110 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Transcript of variants of several lines, entitled The Elegy. var. (crossed out), in the hand of John Mitford, in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. IV, ff. 32r, 33r.
      MS 0211 apparently transcribed from MS 0043.
    - An Elegy written in a Country Church Yard, [between c. 1760 and 1790]; mss.0239; poems.elcc; 7 transcript in an unidentified hand; LELI
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=4660>
      Transcript in an unidentified hand, beginning "The curfeu tolls the knell of parting day", in a commonplace book, entitled Old songs & other poems, "in two hands, c.1760-90, containing transcribed verse and prose of the 17th and 18th centuries".
    - An Elegy Written in a Country Church Yard, [1750s?]; mss.0240; poems.elcc; 3 transcript in an unidentified hand, partial [ll. 1-92], in a manuscript volume "bound in dark brown leather which is gilt embossed with decorations and gilt tooling. There is marbling on both inside covers and endpapers. The back board is detached"; LELI
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=4659>
      Transcript of ll. 1-92 in an unidentified hand, beginning "The curfew tolls the knell of parting day", in a Commonplace-book owned by the Lewis family. It is "in two hands, containing prose and poetry on diverse topics (written partly in the first half of the eighteenth century, partly in the mid eighteenth century); the signatures of Kath Lewis and Johana Lewis are visible on the flyleaf".
    - An elegy written in a country churchyard [by] ... author of The cat and vase, [c. 1765]; mss.0248; poems.elcc; [?] transcript in the hand of David Garrick; FOLG
      Microfilm copy available in Microfilm Collection, FILM Fo. 118.3a, Microfilm of W.a.118, 1 microfilm reel: negative, 12:1, 6 feet; 35 mm.
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 26 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=36725>
      Transcript in the hand of David Garrick in his Poetical miscellany of David Garrick (22 leaves).
    - Elegy written in a country churchyard 1809, mss.0249; poems.elcc; [?] transcript in the hand of John Ardagh of Thurles; FOLG
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 26 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=36728>
      Transcript in the hand of John Ardagh of Thurles, a later addition on a blank verso, in an autograph volume by William Havard entitled Jeu d'esprit (c. 1733-1775).
    - Elegy Written in a Country Church-Yard, 1781/1782; mss.0253; poems.elcc; 6 transcript c. 230 mm x 185 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/07/2010.
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 9 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=138994>
      Transcript of the poem in 32 numbered stanzas in the Strahan Papers, Vol. CVII (ff. 216), Miscellaneous correspondence and papers (1758-1821), ff. 64-66. The transcript follows the MS of John Young's A Criticism on the Elegy Written in a Country Churchyard (ff. 37-63), sent in a letter of Young's (ff. 35-36) to Lord Maitland, which contains instructions about its printing and publication. The transcript is followed by a note (f. 67): "The Author's Compliments to Mr. Strahan. has transcribed over the Elegy as he wishes it printed. Thinks it will stand best between the Advertisement & the Criticism. - The Title as alter'd by Mr Strahan was / A Criticism / on the Elegy / written in a Country Churchyard / being a Continuation / of Dr J---ns Criticism / on the Poems of Gray."
    - [untitled], between 1803 and 1808; mss.0256; poems.elcc; 1 transcript, partial, in the hand of "Richard Harris Barham" (also known as Thomas Ingoldsby); HARV
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 9 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=36729>
      Transcript of the poem, partial, beginning "Approach and read, for thou canst read, the lay", in the hand of "Richard Harris Barham" (also known as Thomas Ingoldsby), in his Commonplace Book (1803-1808), containing poems, paraphrases, epigrams, and conundrums in English, Latin, Greek, and French (62 leaves, 21 cm.), f. 46v.
    - Elegy, written in a country-churchyard, [undated]; mss.0260; poems.elcc; 4 transcript in an unidentified hand; HARV
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 9 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=36733>
      Transcript of the poem, in an unidentified hand, from the Egerton MS 2400.
      In the same file there is another transcript of the poem, from the Fraser MS, in the hand of the donor of the two items James Freeman Clarke.
    - [?], [after 1751]; mss.0261; poems.elcc; [?] transcript in an unidentified hand; HARV
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 9 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=36722>
      Transcript of the poem, in an unidentified hand, in an 18th-century Commonplace Book (176 p., 21 cm.), f. 79.
    - An epitaph, [between 1768 and 1769]; mss.0270; poems.elcc; 1 transcript, partial (epitaph) 190mm x 130mm (volume); YALE
      Parks, Stephen et al. (ed.), Osborn Collection First-Line Index. New Haven: Beinecke Library, Yale University, 2005, 326, item H0937
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 16 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10636>
      Transcript, partial, entitled An epitaph, in a Commonplace book entitled Amusements 1768-69, a manuscript, in two hands, of a collection of several dozen primarily serious poems and poetical extracts, many on moral and elegiac subjects.
    - A poem wrote in a country churchyard, mss.0276; poems.elcc; [?] transcript; YALE
      Parks, Stephen et al. (ed.), Osborn Collection First-Line Index. New Haven: Beinecke Library, Yale University, 2005, 760, item T0441
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 23 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10648>
      Transcript entitled A poem wrote in a country churchyard.
    - An elegy written in a country churchyard, [between 1766 and 1800]; mss.0277; poems.elcc; [?] transcript in the hand of James Forbes; YALE
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 23 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10630>
      Transcript, entitled An elegy written in a country churchyard, in James Forbes' Commonplace book, 1766-1800, vol. I "Poems on Several Occasions Collected from Different Authors", a manuscript of a collection of approximately 150 poems and excerpts, primarily epitaphs and elegies, poems in praise of virtues, odes dedicated to women, and poems on nature and weather.
    - Stanzas wrote in a churchyard in the country, [before 1805]; mss.0278; poems.elcc; [?] transcript 290mm x 230mm (volume); YALE
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 23 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10641>
      Transcript, entitled Stanzas wrote in a churchyard in the country, in the Frances Boscawen and Julia Evelyn Commonplace Book, a collection of verse by various authors and some original verse, contains about 100 poems copied by the authors, beginning in 1746.
    - An elegy, [late 18th/early 19th century]; mss.0279; poems.elcc; [?] transcript 210mm x 160mm (volume); YALE
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 23 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10647>
      Transcript, entitled An elegy, in a late 18th/early 19th century Commonplace Book, a collection of verse (including original poems), letters, drawings, etc., compiled by Martha, Ann, and William Dickinson (1746-1823).
    - An elegy written in a country churchyard, mss.0280; poems.elcc; [?] transcript; YALE
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 23 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10649>
      Transcript entitled An elegy written in a country churchyard.
    - An elegy written in a country churchyard, [late 18th century]; mss.0281; poems.elcc; [?] transcript in an unidentified hand 220mm x 130mm (volume); YALE
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 23 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10627>
      Transcript, entitled An elegy written in a country churchyard, in a late 18th century, anonymous Commonplace Book (4 vols.), which contains more than 1100 numbered extracts from works by various authors; a number of the poems are signed or initialed by William Warren Porter (1776-1804) or his sister, so possibly the books were compiled by a member of the Porter family.
    - An elegy, written in a country churchyard, [late 18th century]; mss.0282; poems.elcc; [?] transcript in an unidentified hand 220mm x 130mm (volume); YALE
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 23 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10626>
      Transcript, entitled An elegy, written in a country churchyard, in a late 18th century, anonymous Commonplace Book (4 vols.), which contains more than 1100 numbered extracts from works by various authors; a number of the poems are signed or initialed by William Warren Porter (1776-1804) or his sister, so possibly the books were compiled by a member of the Porter family.
    - An elegy, written in a country churchyard...1751. In print, [c. 1751]; mss.0283; poems.elcc; [?] transcript in the hand of Richard Gifford 240mm x 130mm (volume); YALE
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 23 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10629>
      Transcript, entitled An elegy, written in a country churchyard...1751. In print, in Richard Gifford's Miscellany (62 p.), which contains prose meditations, romantic and other poems, and Greek and Latin extracts from classical works.
    - Elegy written in a country churchyard, [before 1854]; mss.0284; poems.elcc; [?] transcript in the hand of John Freeman Milward Dovaston 190mm x 120mm (volume); YALE
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 23 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10634>
      Transcript in the hand of John Freeman Milward Dovaston, entitled Elegy written in a country churchyard, in his autograph Select, and Miscellaneous Poems, Scraps, Mottos &c, 1773 and later, a Commonplace book of verse by Dovaston and others.
  - [Epitaph on a Child], Here, freed from pain, secure from misery, lies; 1884; poems.epld
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 104
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 209-210
    Written in mid-June 1758 at the request of Thomas Wharton to commemorate his eldest son Robin who died in April 1758. First published in
    Gosse (ed.), Works (1884), vol. I, 126
    , from the transcript made by Alexander Dyce.
    - [untitled], [1758?]; mss.0049; poems.epld; 1 autograph fair copy; MOLI
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 37, 82
      Jones, Thomas Gray, Scholar (1937), "Register of Gray Autograph Manuscripts", VI. 20(a) epitaph on a child, 181
      Munby (ed.), Sale Catalogues (1971), Evans sale (27-29 November 1845), lot 624(?), 11, Sotheby's sale (12 August 1847), lot 89, 27, Sotheby's sale (28 August 1851), lot 53(?), 41, Sotheby's sale (4 August 1854), lot 228(?), 69
      W[right]., Catalogue (1851), [lot 53?,] 9
      Nelson, Christine, "extra-illustrated copy of Gray's Odes". E-mail to the editor, 14 November 2006
      Autograph fair copy, here untitled but endorsed 'Epitaph on a Child' in an unidentified hand, bound into Gray's copy of Odes ( 1757 ).
    - Epitaph on a Child, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0050; poems.epld; 1 transcript in the hand of John Mitford 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 38, 82
      Transcript in the hand of John Mitford, apparently from a Gray autograph and hence annotated "N.B. in Grays writing.", in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", f. 74r.
    - Epitaph on a Child, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0051; poems.epld; 1 transcript in the hand of John Mitford 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 39, 82
      Transcript in the hand of John Mitford, here beginning "Here free from Pain...", in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", f. 182r.
    - Epitaph on a Child, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0048; poems.epld; 1 transcript in the hand of John Mitford, crossed out 180 mm x 110 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Transcript in the hand of John Mitford, here beginning "Here free from Pain..." (crossed out), in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. IV, f. 28r.
    - [untitled], [before 1869]; mss.0052; poems.epld; [1?] transcript in the hand of Alexander Dyce; VAUK
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 40, 82
      Transcript in the hand of Alexander Dyce, used for first publication.
  - [Epitaph on Mrs Clerke], Lo! where this silent marble weeps; 1758 (pr. 1759); poems.epmc
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 52
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 207-209
    Written not long before 31 January 1758 presumably at the request of John Clerke to commemorate his wife Jane who died 27 April 1757 aged 31. Inscribed on a mural tablet in St George's parish church, Beckenham, Kent, 1758. First published, as "An Epitaph copied from a Tomb-stone in a Country Church Yard", in The Gentleman's Magazine, October 1759.
    - [untitled], 31 January 1758; mss.0053; poems.epmc; [1?] autograph; HULI
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 41, 83
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 266, vol. ii, 559-561 (subscription required)
      Autograph of an 18-line version, here untitled and beginning "Lo! where this little Marble weeps" in a letter to Edward Bedingfield, 31 January 1758.
    - [untitled], [1759?]; mss.0054; poems.epmc; [1?] transcript possibly in the hand of Richard Hurd; HARC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 42, 83
      Pearce, E. H. and Leonard Whibley (eds.), The Correspondence of Richard Hurd and William Mason (Cambridge, 1932), 168
      Transcript, possibly in the hand of Richard Hurd, here untitled and headed "By Mr. Gray", together with a Latin version, in the papers of Richard Hurd.
    - Epitaph on Mrs. Clarke, 1780[?]; mss.0228; poems.epmc; 4 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/03/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled Epitaph on Mrs. Clarke (p. 109) (Epitaph. I. [p. 111]). The poem, which is annotated "This Lady, the Wife of Dr. Clarke, Physician at Epsom, died April, 27, 1757; and is buried in the Church of Beckenham, Kent" on the title page, is part of a section called Poems, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 129), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
    - [untitled], 1769[?]; mss.0245; poems.epmc; 1 transcript in an unidentified hand 220 mm x 162 mm; BDLN; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in the SCRR at the RSL, Bodleian Library, on 11/03/2010.
      Crum (ed.), First-Line Index (1969), vol. I, 527, item L511 (no author attribution)
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=73561> (no author attribution)
      Transcript in an unidentified hand, headed "& Where is this Epitaph", in a volume entitled Memorials of Richard Gough, volume II, section I. "Poems preserved by Richard Gough Esq.". The volume, which is 14 5/8 x 9 3/4 in. in size and contains 320 leaves, is one of two Volumes of Poems and other interesting Memorials of Richard Gough, Esq., F.R.S., F.S.A.., collected by J[ohn] B[owyer] Nichols (Summary Catalogue, 32551).
  - [Epitaph on Mrs Mason], Tell them, though 'tis an awful thing to die; [1767] (pr. 1784); poems.epmm
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 105
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 255-256
    Written between 27 March and 23 May 1767 for Mason's wife Mary who died on 27 March 1767 aged 28. Inscribed on a monument in Bristol Cathedral, [1767]. First published in The New Foundling Hospital for Wit (London, new edn. 1784 ), vi. 45. Transcripts of Mason's own epitaph on his wife beginning "Take, holy Earth, all that my soul holds dear", are at PwV 304 and 1010(ii), Portland Collection, University of Nottingham, Nottingham, UK.
    - Epitaph, [1767?]; mss.0055; poems.epmm; [1?] autograph and autograph transcript; HARC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 43, 83
      Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 256
      Autograph of Gray's four lines, preceding a transcript in Gray's hand of the 12 lines composed by Mason, the whole entitled Epitaph, endorsed in the hand of Richard Hurd "Mr. Mason's Ep. on his wife in Mr. Gray's hand-writing", in the papers of Richard Hurd.
    - [untitled], November 1805; mss.0056; poems.epmm; 1 transcript in the hand of Norton Nicholls; ETON
      Mitford (ed.), Works (1843), vol. v, 40
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 44, 83
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), vol. iii, 1294
      Transcript in the hand of Norton Nicholls, in his MS Reminiscences of Gray, p. 12.
  - [Epitaph on Sir William Williams], Here, foremost in the dangerous paths of fame; 1775; poems.epww
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 104-105
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 238-240
    Written between May and August 1761 at the request of one of the executors of Sir William Williams, a politician and soldier Gray briefly met early in October 1760, who died 27 April 1761 on an expedition against Belle Ile. First published, as Epitaph II. On Sir William Williams, in Mason's Poems ( 1775 ), 62.
    - [untitled], August 1761; mss.0059; poems.epww; [1?] autograph; NYPL
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 45, 83
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 339, vol. ii, 745-746 (subscription required)
      Autograph, here untitled, in a letter to William Mason, August 1761.
    - Epitaph on Sr W J Williams, [after 1771]; mss.0060; poems.epww; 1 transcript in the hand of William Mason; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 46, 83
      Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 105, for variants and rejected stanza
      Transcript in the hand of William Mason, here entitled Epitaph on Sr W J Williams with two variants of l. 12 in "Variations" and a "Rejected Stanza", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. III, 1108.
    - Epitaph on Sir Willm. Williams, 1780[?]; mss.0229; poems.epww; 4 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/03/2007.